[Music]
this
good evening and good day to everybody i
hope you're doing very well and welcome
to this 79th live episode of ask abidjit
so before we begin let me just do a few
greetings let's see who all is there raj
kumar singh
srishti vlog sony singh dungar singh
johan
bagh super duper explorer
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you wherever you are
it's great to have you all with us
so as you know today i'm gonna take a
bunch of questions from the comments
that you have uh
that you have asked in the comments so
shall we begin shall we go right right
into it
let us
uh begin with the questions
and question number one is by wisdom bro
wisdom bro says is it true that the
amazon forest is actually man-made i
heard
graham hancock mentioning it in a
podcast
yes so until now uh the amazon until
very recently the amazon rainforest has
been looked upon as a pristine
wilderness untouched by humans and that
sort of thing
but in recent times as more research new
research has been conducted in this
enormous rainforest it has been several
surprising things have come to light
first of all when you do a leader
scanning of the of the
terrain of the amazon rainforest lidar
is a laser kind of thing it's a
technology that uses laser to
non-destructively peer through the
forest and the leaves and see
actually what kind of ground covering is
is there what is the terrain like
so when you do lidar analysis lidar
scanning of the terrain of the amazon
rainforest you find there are lots of
human structures hidden
beneath the thick canopy of the forest
lots and lots so it looked like it looks
like there was once an extensive network
of human habitations and you know like
cities towns villages even metropolises
in the entire amazon rainforest area
that's point number one
point number two is that um if you
analyze the species of trees
that exist in this enormous rainforest
so so let me
bring the map on and let me show you
where this rainforest is so
uh
so essentially the amazon rainforest is
this big region in south america
mostly brazil this entire green part is
essentially more or less
the amazon rainforest especially this
part here if you can see my mouse
pointer that area is an enormous
territory that is covered with
rainforest right just for tropical
forests
so that's what it is so when you do an
analysis of the uh of the species of
plants and trees that you have in the
amazon for rainforest you find that
approximately 50 percent
of the trees belong to just around one
percent of the species
which is not a natural thing so it looks
like many of these uh
species of trees were planted there by
human beings and it has emerged in
recent times that there is a certain
kind of soil that has been used in the
past in the amazon rainforest a super
soil of of sorts
to uh
to engage in agriculture and growing
certain species of trees and plants and
all that so it has emerged that in the
past for at least 10 13 000 years
human beings
the natives of south america and this
region have been planting certain
species of trees and plants in this
region
and that is what gave rise to the
majority of the amazon rainforest
and uh significant amounts of
research is happening right now and
you're finding more and more evidence of
that so in the past there were these
clusters or islands
of trees and plantations that eventually
grew into the amazon rainforest now how
did this happen what happened to all the
human inhabitation
what happened is that the european
colonization happened the spanish the
spaniards came into this region south
america
they
they wiped out the natives they
destroyed the natives
and they also brought in many of the old
world diseases like smallpox etc
which ravaged the populations of south
america and the native americans even in
north america right and that's what led
to essentially
the wiping out of entire
cultures and civilizations
and in just a few years or decades
entire cities fell into disrepair they
were abandoned because everyone died and
within 10 20 30 40 50 years you have
forest growing all over it
and that's how all these great
cities and inhabitations just
disappeared below beneath the canopy of
the forest and today you have a vast
rainforest there
so in short the amazon forest actually
is indeed
uh the outgrowth of human plantations
and yeah you could say that it it
originates as a man-made forest so that
is indeed correct
arnold says what is a secret society how
is it formed and what are the roles it
plays
any major secret society that impacted
the global geopolitics well it's an
interesting question no doubt but the
thing about secret societies is that
they are secret
they will not make their presence felt
they will not advertise their existence
and the more successful a secret society
is the more secret and hidden it remains
it will not make itself known that is
the secret of its success
right
so secret societies have been in
existence for a long time essentially
forever you could say
uh in the 19th century the
the so-called philosopher karl marx he
spoke about the invisible hand
which essentially says there is a
class of people group of people the
so-called super elite or whatever you
want to call them who
act behind the scenes who are hidden
from view and who pull the strings of
global geopolitics and affairs and the
economy and everything
so karl marx alluded to this and it's
always been known that there have been
such a secret societies and
secrets strata secret power structures
extra
governmental extra democratic power
structures that exist throughout the
world including even today and they have
been given a number of names
there is the alleged
the alleged
uh nine secret men or nine special men
of ashok or chandragupta maury or
somebody else that suppose that
supposedly exists possibly even today in
india who knows then there is the
so-called
illuminati that people talk about
which may or may not exist and may
actually exist who knows the so-called
illuminati and then you have these so
called
not the so called the this the
masons the masonic society which now
actually doesn't hide its existence
anymore but it still doesn't rival its
purpose so the stone masons the free
sorry the freemasons they're called
right and they have chapters or charters
or whatever you want to call them across
the world including in india
um
let's let's take a look at what they
look like right
they even have a website and all that in
india
so let's see
uh freemasons india the grand lodge of
india so it's a secret society which is
not so secreting anymore but their
purpose their objectives are still
secret
they say that their objective is to
create a brotherhood of men
and women nowadays also etc
but their origins are kind of obscure
they seem to have an origin
in judaism or christianity it's clearly
an abrahamic origin a european origin
right and they have their chapters and
societies lodges they call them all
across the world including in india
let's take a look at the website of the
grand lodge of india what and
many
many uh prominent indians have been
members of this secret society and we
still don't know what is the purpose of
the society so that is very interesting
so as you can see there are very
prominent indians and people of indian
birth like rudyard kipling the great
racist poet
and various other very prominent people
who somehow our members have been
members
of
the masonic lodge grand lodge of india
one wonders why and one wonders what the
purpose of this was
but i am not going to speculate about
things that i don't know much about so
i'm just telling you that this is the
way it is
these are the facts that are well known
and
so that's what secret societies are
we know some of them we some of them the
real powerful ones may be hidden but
that's what it is so any major secret
society that impacted global geopolitics
we don't know
we don't know they would be secret they
would not make their existence known but
it's a very interesting topic and it is
not conspiracy theories these are all
facts
these societies do exist
okay something else
so two questions we have here about
ayurveda kostub says what do you think
is better ayurveda or modern science
and location says when i typed ayurveda
in google the wikipedia result shows or
contains hatred of ayurveda the exact
words are
the theory and practice of ayurveda is
pseudoscientific the indian medical
association describes ayurvedic
practitioners who claim to practice
medicine as quacks
why so much hatred for indian origin
things
and the same exists for covax in as well
well let me first speak about covaxing
covax in the indian vaccine for the
corona virus is the safest and most
efficacious vaccine that we have
across the world
for this coronavirus pandemic co-vaccine
is the safest one and the most effective
one
better than all the other modern iron
pfizer and cyno wax and all the other
vaccines and it's safer than all of
these vaccines
so first of all the indian vaccine is
the best vaccine many people in the u.s
are clamoring for the introduction of
the indian vaccine there but that won't
be allowed because you know what
big pharma wants to make money
and everything in the us is driven by
money including health care including
people's lives no one cares that's how
it is that's the kind of society you
have in the u.s right so the thing about
uh hatred of ayurveda it's you know what
it looks like hatred it's not really
hatred it is fear
see ayurveda is a system that has been
around for thousands of years
it has been improved upon gradually over
centuries and millennia
and
our ancestors the ancient indian
scientists medical professionals etc
from thousands of years ago
they found these various herbs compounds
other things by
a long exhaustive process of trial and
error and these are all natural
substances natural
herbal extracts and compounds and all
that which don't have any side effects
because these are naturally occurring
substances and combinations of
substances right
and they are known to have been very
effective in treating various uh
illnesses
now if you look at scientific if you
look at uh chinese traditional medicine
that is now part of the whose
spiel kind of you know in a way they
consider it to be mainstream medicine
but ayurveda is not because the indian
government isn't well it hasn't taken
much of an initiative in the past even
today perhaps there are no institutes of
ayurveda the proper institutes that uh
bring ayurveda into the 21st century
scientific uh domain and all that so
it's still regarded as kind of herbal or
tribal medicine or you know
pseudoscientific thing and the thing is
ayurvedic
treatments may take a longer time but
they are more effective
to treat various illnesses in the west
especially in the us everything
everybody is on medication
you know
pharma big pharma is a huge industry
it's a huge industry it is extremely
lucrative all medications cost a fortune
medical insurance costs a fortune it's a
huge scam
that is being perpetrated on the people
of the united states and now it is
already also been transferred into india
20 30 years ago medicines used to cost 2
rupees 3 rupees 5 rupees 10 rupees today
the same medicines cost hundreds of
rupees or thousands of rupees so the
whole scam has been transferred into
india and the so-called indian medical
association is part of this let's not
mince any words
all doctors
want
to be on the payroll of various pharma
companies so that they can make more
money it's a it's
it is an industry
right
it's a business they don't they don't
want you to
be cured they want you to be sick
forever so that they can keep giving you
medicines
and so the doctor keeps on earning and
the pharma companies keep an earning
and ayurveda is a big obstacle to that
because ayurveda actually cures your
illnesses and it's been known to have
been doing that for thousands of years
and therefore it's best if ayurveda is
demonized and described with severe
scientific so that people will stay away
from it so that big pharma can keep
making money this is the big scam that
we are all living today especially since
since you know when
so that's what i can say now what is
better i would rather modern science you
know ayurveda
is a proven system
okay
now
uh it is always
better if you bring the study of
ayurveda in a systematic way into the
21st century medical context and you you
study it from a modern pharmacological
uh perspective right so the various
ayurvedic treatments compounds it is
always good if you can analyze them from
a 21st century scientific biochemical
perspective
and codify it in in a modern sense the
way the chinese are doing with
traditional chinese medicine
so today traditional chinese medicine
has given rise to several 21st century
treatments for for instance
late night late 20th century early 21st
century the arty mission that was
discovered as a treatment for malaria
that came out of traditional chinese
medicine right there will be so many
such treatments that are still hidden
within ayurveda which are not being
brought to light because
it is being demonized in this manner so
it is incumbent on the indian government
on the indian establishment to uh
to bring ayurveda into the 21st century
context and uh merge ayurveda with the
cutting edge latest technology and
research
that would be the best possible outcome
for everyone so that's what i would like
to see happen
so
that in short is
is about ayurveda
okay there are a couple of comments not
exactly questions or naveen kumar says i
am from tamil nadu not everyone in tamil
nadu likes periyar that the creature
more percentage people hate
hate that guy but politicians only use
him for political reasons unfortunately
eighty percent of media in tamil nadu is
under the control of dravidian
politicians it's just the media
propaganda i am in indian i will always
be indian please read my comment in the
next episode so here we are i'm reading
a comment naveen very very nice to see
this and thank you for
expressing your opinion the second
comment is from indic renaissance i'm
from tamil nadu india and not everyone
is anti-civilizational degenerates but
yes subversion is real here and they
keep pushing this abrahamic narrative
and pushing the so-called tamil identity
but i'm always a hindu indian you know
in the past until the 1960s 70s tamil
nadu was seen
as
even more indian than the rest of india
like north india etc more traditionally
indian than the rest of india
right that's after tamil nadu used to be
and then see what happened what's
happened in the last 30 40 years
the entire civilizational structure has
been uprooted eradicated and today you
see what comes in the news from tamil
nadu you see what's in the news right
now what's trending on twitter right now
with that girl who was forced to commit
suicide by missionaries so tamil nadu
has been totally destinated today
maybe it's not totally
resonated but the
majority of the people are not able to
express their opinions and whatever is
in the mainstream in the media the
politicians etc they are trying to uh
push an anti-india soft separatist
anti-hindu hindu phobic uh narrative
which is now which has now become the
mainstream in tamil nadu every week you
see an ancient temple being bulldozed in
tamil nadu for what reason i don't
understand
right so tamil nadu the politics has
become virulently anti-india anti-hindu
anti-civilization anti-culture and they
are trying to push the missionary agenda
it's very clear let's say it's openly
right so that's what's happening and
it's very unfortunate and if it
continues like this india is going to
fragment i'm telling you
because what holds india together what
has been holding india together for 10
000 years is indian civilization and
culture
which is not tamil culture or or north
indian culture or whatever it is simply
indian culture
if you look at the rich history of tamil
nadu
before this third-rate dravidian
anti-hindu anti-indian parties came into
existence these periarist parties
the ones that uh worship bishop caldwell
these people you know politics is all
about creating fractional fragmentation
in society it's all about creating the
illusion of oppression so that the and
then you claim that i am we are the ones
who are gonna save you
so that's the game these politicians are
playing but if you look at the rich
history of the tamil people
it has been at the vanguard at the
forefront of indian culture
and the same goes for the entirety of
southern india not just tamil nadu
kerala also karnataka and there are all
these places if you look at the great uh
dynasties in tamil nadu in southern
india the cheras the pandas the cholas
and so many more
they have been at the forefront
of promoting indian culture not just in
india but even way beyond india's shores
so it is
disappointing and unfortunate that tamil
nadu is now at the forefront of this
anti-hindu anti-civilization movement
it's just sad
and it shows how easy it is to
manipulate
the minds
of people especially young people it's
so easy to manipulate the minds of young
people using
the education system the media the
entertainment industry
and uh
and politics so that's what we are
seeing today but that also gives you the
solution of how we can undo this
when the time is right
okay agastya says uh i was wondering
what are your thoughts
about
rc majumdar as a source for learning
about india's ancient history are his
books credible and something i can use
to further my knowledge on the topic
so rc majumdar in my opinion in my
experience has been uh an excellent
historian uh clearly
much of what he has written has to be
treated with a little bit of caution
because it is
it is something that was written a very
long time ago
uh i don't remember exactly when he
wrote his great uh his major works but
it would be in the 1940s 1560s and
latest in the 70s so that's at least 50
years before today and therefore much of
the content of the books that he has
written
much of that
is possibly
outdated
but much of it is still very relevant
for instance every historian in the past
has
expressed
well i believe and and
a belief in the rn in the in the
in the veracity of the rn version theory
because that was the prevalent theory at
the time and therefore they saw nothing
wrong with
uh ex
with writing about it as if it is a
known fact because it was
the accepted wisdom at the time today we
know this theory has been totally
debunked it's completely incorrect from
all angles
and yet all of these great writers in
the past they they put forth the iron
vision theory as a fact
as if it's a it's a fact and there are
other aspects also
in
in various parts of ancient
texts from 50 years ago 70 years ago
which may be outdated today we have
better information
but yet
all of this work that has been done for
especially by ourselves
it is still very valuable because if you
look at his works about uh for instance
the gupta dynasty the vacation
the
the indian influence in southeast asia
etc i think there's almost nobody after
him who has written about these things
in great detail and therefore his works
are still
very valuable reference works
for these parts of our history
so i think rc majumdar is an excellent
source even today for learning about
india's ancient history and for learning
about india's influence beyond india's
shores especially in southeast asia and
eastern asia his books are excellent of
course you have to keep in mind that
this is sort of
these books were written written at
least 50 years ago so some parts of the
books may be outdated and you may have
to update your in your knowledge from
other sources as well so keep that in
mind if you keep that in mind and read
intelligently you will learn a lot from
rc majima's work i would
from his works especially his 11 or 12
volume work i think 11 volume work
history and
culture of the indian people i think
that's what it's called i think it's an
excellent reference work and i think
it's something that is still
very valuable from the perspective of
learning india's history so yes i would
certainly recommend his works
anish says the pandemic has forced a
majority of the businesses and
professions in education to adapt to the
online working from home mode or
functioning this has reduced the working
capital and expenditure for most of the
businesses especially those in
technology yes
in your opinion should those professions
and businesses and educational courses
which require no practical physical
presence continue in the same way of
working post the pandemic i think
that the world has changed forever
uh
it's it was called the new normal in
2020 while we are living the new normal
today in 2022.
uh the entire mode of working has
changed working from home is here to
stay in my opinion uh
you know i think if it is done the right
way it can even even
it can give rise to better productivity
as well
so i think that
many of these businesses professions are
going to
continue the practice of working online
working from home working from wherever
you are
and i see nothing wrong with that there
are especially in technology in software
etc you can work from anywhere in the
world and you can all
you can always collaborate and interface
via zoom or whatever
whatever mode you have
and it's just like being in office and
you can get all your work done just as
well if not better
working from home uh so especially in
technology this is going to be that way
high technology software development and
all these things it's going to be there
it's going to continue i see nothing
wrong with that but there are certain
industries etc in which you need to be
physically present especially those that
are in the engineering domain and other
things like that in which case you have
to be physically present and you have to
create physical products and all that in
which case
things won't change much
when it comes to education
it's a
it's a mixed bag
so for
effective education you need a
face-to-face interface interfa
interaction
between teachers and students
as as adults you can deal with the
working from home environment looking at
a screen and talking to people through a
screen but children need a physical
presence of a teacher you know
of course i have also argued in the past
that children can now just ditch
conventional education and learn
everything online that also works
but i would say that for young children
etc for at least a few years then it is
beneficial to have
an interaction
in
in in
flesh and blood between teachers and
other kids
you know so in so in the case of
education especially uh
primary education up to the third fourth
standard maybe it may be best to go back
to the old style
of sitting in a classroom and working
and studying in a classroom of course
you need a good education system for
that the indian education system is
worthless useless so in that case it
doesn't really make much of a difference
but overall i would say
that the world has changed permanently
people are going to keep on working from
home they're going to keep on working
remotely and uh that's just the way
things are going to be especially with
the meta was coming in even working from
home maybe like working from office
because you may have
the soon have the presence of your
colleagues right there in the room with
you even if you are in your
bedroom or living room
so
things are to change very fast this
decade and it's an evolving situation an
evolving world and let's see where it
takes us but yes the world has certainly
changed
deeply and forever
what steps can be taken by us as a
government as an individual as an
entrepreneur as a vc venture capitalist
angel investor etc so that more and more
deep tech startups emerge from india
that can conquer the whole world's
technologies
so
let's take a look at how all these uh
tech startups emerged in the u.s
so it all emerged in this place called
silicon valley in california right
sun
sun jose san francisco that area
san jose san diego that particularly
it's called
silicon valley right
so what happened is that all of these
technology startups emerged from there
lots of tech startups there was this
entire
environment there that you had lots of
venture capitalists and angel investors
who were looking for uh
new companies new startups to invest in
and there were lots of these uh
technological uh graduates tech
graduates and all that
who were looking to solve problems
solve the problems of the nation of the
society using using technology using
computing and emerging technologies so
this entire confluence of these young
kids who
were tech savvy who were comfortable
with high technology and who wanted to
solve problems and
the presence of all these investors etc
this confluence created silicon valley
so
for something like that to be replicated
in india what needs to be done first of
all the government is already doing all
the right things
to make it easier and easier for
businesses to start up so
today uh you have gst in the past you
did not have gst so
india was not like one nation it was
like a confederation of nations with
their own taxes and all that nonsense so
gst has broken all those very barriers
secondly we have uh
upi payments and all that which has made
it very very easy for people to receive
payments online on the spot using just
mobile phones so it's going to make
credit cards obsolete it's making credit
cards obsolete you know so
india is essentially on the precipice of
a major
entrepreneurial entrepreneurial boom
india in the next 20 years could be
totally different from what we are
seeing today if if the right steps
continue to be taken so we already are
seeing the building blocks being put
into place for a major
uh
boom in entrepreneurship in tech starts
startups etc we also have the startup
india program which is
generating all these unicorns
india has surpassed even china in the
number of unicorns it is producing so
you see very good uh steps being taken
being taken it is we are still in the
infancy of this entire process but in
the next 20 years we could see india
totally being transformed so what can
individuals do individuals youngsters
kids they need to be tech savvy
today
to transform the nation and this and to
solve the nation's problems
you need
software you need apps which can do
these things of course the government
has to do certain things and take care
of certain issues
but you can solve
so many of the world's problems and
start with india you can solve so many
of india's problems using software using
technology so the kids who are uh
teenagers etc today they need to become
tech tech savvy learn various uh
programming languages learn how to code
apps
on whatever platform learn um
learn how to build operating systems all
these things you know
so become really comfortable with
technology and also it's not enough to
be good with technology it's not enough
to be proficient with technology you
also need to understand business you
need to understand the economy you need
to understand personal finances the
finances of running a startup
how to scale a startup how to get
investment how to get funding
how not to get scammed all those things
so this is also very important you know
uh
financial literacy so as individuals you
need to be tech savvy and you need to be
financially literate really financially
literate and savvy that's what needs to
happen entrepreneurs need to obviously
make all the right moves and
learn how to run a business efficiently
lean startup all that you know so all
that stuff you need to learn
as vc as venture capitalist angel
investors you need to be on the lookout
for
agile lightweight
startups run by youngsters
that have the potential to solve
major problems in the country
that's what brings value to society if
you want to become rich you have to
provide value to society at a large
scale if you do that you will become
rich so it's a win-win situation for you
as
an entrepreneur and for society as a
whole
and it is for the vcs the angel
investors to identify
such startups that have the potential to
solve big problems and then fund them
so you need to have the right vision and
you know you need to be able to identify
the talent
so all that is what vcs and angel
investors need to
look out for and as a government
please end corruption in this country
india
the entire governance of india
the low-level politics of india it all
runs on corruption let's not mince words
let's not hide facts the entire country
runs on corruption
so much
of the country's wealth goes into the
wrong pockets
and it is the wealth of the of the
individual citizen you know so in the
government of india needs to find a way
of of starting to to to start to address
this problem of corruption
and to
weed out all the inefficiencies in the
bureaucratic system in the bureaucracy
of india and to make
doing business even easier than it is
right now so india is doing really well
on on the global rankings of ease of
doing business but why can't india be in
the top 10 in the world why not
that would totally unleash the potential
of india
so these are the things that the
government can do so these are a bunch
of things so india is still in
in the infancy of this process
but there's tremendous potential which
we are already seeing and the government
is doing a lot of the right right things
we would like to see that being built
upon by the government and all round you
can do lots of reforms
and totally transform
the entrepreneurial and business
landscape in india and unleash the true
potential of indians
indians have this immense
entrepreneurial spirit it's been there
for thousands of years
right so that's what needs to be
unleashed right now india is a nation in
shackles it is chained it is still a
nation in chains break the chains and
unleash the true potential of india you
will see startups left right and center
india's kids are brilliant just give
them a chance to give them the
opportunity to
use the brilliance to solve india's
problems so that's what the government
needs to do
okay arnov says if the british captured
india by defeating the marathas in the
anglo-maratha wars then how was the last
mughal emperor baadur shazafar still in
india until his death in 1862
was he in power and what was his role in
the 1857 revolt or rather war of
independence
this is a good question
so as we know the marathas had
re-conquered india freed india from the
turks
by the middle of the
18th century and it is from the marathas
that the british
captured power and captured uh control
of india
so the british did not save india from
the turks the marat has had already
freed india from the turks the maratha
empire was from southern india
from large parts of southern india all
the way up to southern afghanistan so
that the turkic
occupation of india had been annihilated
by the marathas and yet
and yet you had
a mughal emperor in india now this
mughal emperor who was in power in delhi
was essentially the mayor of delhi
and even less than the mayor of the of
delhi he was the mayor of the red fort
or whatever place he was inhabiting
that's it he had no real power
it was just a tight tuller position of
the mughal emperor
a mughal emperor with no power
whatsoever even in delhi that's what it
was badur zafar was nothing more than
the head of a household who had power
only within his household he did not
even have power of life and death or
policy making or anything in the city of
delhi
so that's how he was he was a powerless
toothless emperor emperor only in name
but for some reason the marathas allowed
the uh
institution of the mughal emperor to
continue somehow for for some reason so
this is something that is uh i am not
sure why they did that maybe i need to
bring in some expert in maratha history
and we can perhaps have a discussion on
that so that may be something i will do
in the future
but what i can say is that the
so-called mughal emperor was an emperor
only in name
king of your own castle king of your two
bhk apartment that sort of thing so
that's what he was
okay and bahadur shah zafar was the
so-called last mughal emperor of india
even though he had no power his role in
the 1857 war of independence was as the
titular figurehead
for some reason
the the people the the fighters the the
uh the indians who are fighting the
british and trying to win independence
they declared him as their titular
emperor or figurehead or something just
just in name he did not really
have the uh ability to issue orders to
them and they would not obey him it was
just in name right
and uh then as we know
for whatever uh
bunch of reasons we lost the war of
independence 1857
and then there was this terrible
genocide at least 10 million indians
were killed by the british in the next
5-10 years
as
an act of
revenge
and this fellow bador shazafar he was
sent to rangoon i think
as a sort of exile
and that's where he died and that's
where he is buried so that is the story
in short of bahadur shazafar
an emperor only in name and nothing more
wisdom bro says who will reach faster
through their ancient civilizational
roots
india
north europe or eastern europe
so i would say that the
cultures that are the closest to their
roots have the potential to reach their
ancient civilizational roots the fastest
so in the case of europe
uh they are completely deracinated they
have lost all contact with their
ancestral
civilizational cultural roots which is
the old indo-european culture
so the culture 2000 years ago in europe
in various parts of europe was very
similar to the ancient
uh indian culture of that time the same
gods were worshiped the same values were
espoused the same principles were there
and you had a lot of
local manifestations of this vast
culture so that's what we had in europe
and then it was all uprooted wiped out
destroyed by christianity as we know
very well it's been extensively
documented
so
europe has been divorced or or
derecinated from its roots for about at
least at least a thousand years
depending on where you are
in eastern europe in the slavic world
uh this happened more recently maybe
five six hundred years ago
so the slavic world is probably closer
to its uh indo-european roots
than let's say western europe
the nordic countries the the so-called
former viking countries the scandinavian
countries
they are i would say in some ways closer
to their roots than western europe the
vatican all that all that region right
because christianity was introduced
later in these regions
when it comes to india
we
to a large extent
in some way in some form or the other
are still very much close to our
civilizational roots many of us still
practice in some form some broken form
our
ancient culture which is nowadays called
hinduism which is actually dharma in its
various
manifestations
and it is also practiced in large parts
of asia
in some form or the other it is called
buddhism in some places it is called
something else somewhere else but it is
practiced in various forms in this
region so it is much easier for india
and those parts of asia to revert to
their civilizational roots
uh compared to
various other parts of the world like
europe
but uh it is also possible that hinduism
itself will be wiped out of india in the
next 50 or 100 years because we are
seeing signs of that the government is
the governance system is deeply hindu
phobic hindus have no right to control
their own places of worship the temples
the laws the practices the policies are
all hindu phobic
in tamil nadu every week a new temp
one more temple is being bulldozed
ancient temples are being bulldozed and
so on and so forth so india is actually
the world's most endophobic country if
it continues like this
in the next 50 years there'll be no more
hinduism it's quite possible and as you
can see people are so devastated
deracinated especially people who go
through the indian education system they
are ashamed of being indians ashamed of
being hindus ashamed of hinduism ah
hinduism backward misogynistic
patriarchal
primitive
all that right so that's the impression
they have that's what their teachers
teach them
so that's the state of india today so
who knows what's going to happen in the
future
one hopes that uh
that indian culture will
undergo renaissance one hopes
that would be good for the world
as a whole but let's see
the future is still up for grabs right
now
ayan chakravarthy says um
what
what was cleanliness spreading
information fashion in ancient india
like
so let us talk about cleanliness okay i
will take the cleanliness part of the
question
so if we look at
um
let's let's just take a look at hard
data so i recently was talking to dr
neeraj
his podcast is coming up in a couple of
days on this channel
so uh
dr deraj has access to lots of ancient
human remains from across the length and
the breadth of india
and
he was telling me that when you examine
these remains
various ancient india indian human
remains ancient skeletons of people from
various uh
chronological time frames of india and
various geographical parts of india what
you see is very striking that all of
these ancient human remains are in
excellent physical condition excellent
health
you don't find signs of diseases
illnesses lifestyle problems or any such
thing
you will see this invariably across
india
north south east west all across india
the remains are in excellent physical
condition
they may have died of old age or
whatever
but for whatever age they died they are
in excellent condition so what you find
is that
the health
of people of ordinary people in ancient
india was excellent exceptionally good
compared to what you see in other parts
of the world if you see ancient roman
skeletons ancient skeletons in the
celtic regions of europe for instance
ancient viking skeletons and so on you
see all kinds of pathologies
if you look at the
if you find a skeleton you can actually
sample the soil in the abdominal part of
the of the
of the skeleton and you can do a
pathological analysis and see what kind
of bacteria etc were there in the
abdominal region in the digestive tract
of the person and you can find you can
determine if that person had any uh
parasites like worms and all that and
you find that people in ancient europe
invariably had digestive systems riddled
with worms tape worms round worms and
whatnot you don't find that in india
so you find that india's cleanliness
hygiene health was exceptionally good
and why is it so
it's because of indian culture indian
culture so today what you have in india
is there is that life is very fast you
wake up and you rush out of bed and you
brush your teeth in three seconds
grab a cup of coffee and you're out of
the house going to office and you work
15 hours a day or whatever 12 hours and
then you come home and crash and sleep
that's all you do so there is no time to
take care of yourself today in india
especially if you are a younger
professional or whatever right but in
ancient india life was very different
india was a very settled society
very prosperous society
and cleanly less was paramount if you
look at the rituals of cleanliness and
all that you see that indians put
ancient indians put a very high premium
on cleanliness
you could not do things before you took
a bath and did all the procedure all
that in the morning of of cleansing
yourself
brushing your teeth with
acacia twigs and all that so cleanliness
is something that was paramount in india
in in it i think essentially india
taught the world what cleanliness and
hygiene is
and you see signs of this all across
even if you go back 5000 years before
today in the sindhu region you will find
that indian cities in the saraswati
hindu region
had excellent drainage systems better
than what you find today in modern india
right
and india
is the civilization that developed the
flush toilet
india had dentistry india had everything
so cleanliness and health and hygiene
is something that was exceptional in
india
and
that once again tells you that india is
the true cradle of civilization you know
so that's what i can say
in brief
umesh prasad says in
one of your podcasts
you spoke about cyber warfare
and that it could be the form of world
war iii in that case what would be its
impact on underdeveloped or developing
countries good question
so what i said is that cyber warfare is
one of the new domains of warfare today
so you have
various domains of warfare that
transcend what traditional warfare has
all been about
traditionally warfare has been about
land sea and air
that's 21st century or early 20th
that's 20th century and early 21st
century warfare
war on land war at sea that's the navy
and war in the air that's the air force
today you have all all kinds of other
domains cyber warfare is one such domain
of warfare then you have space space is
now a new domain of warfare and there is
psychological warfare and so much so
much more so all of this will come
together in a big synthesis
whenever the next big war is fought
so cyber warfare is going to be one of
those now
in an underdeveloped country
uh the governance system and all will
still be quite primitive it will not be
digitized it will not be computerized
and therefore there's no point of
attacking such a country with a cyber
attack because they don't have any cyber
capabilities or infrastructure to speak
about right
so under developed and developed country
and developing countries won't really be
a major uh factor
in a big war like world war three
world war three if it happens we don't
want it to happen ever but if a major
war happens in the future it's going to
be between the biggest powers in the
world the top powers the great powers
let's say the us
china russia india
eu perhaps
right japan these are major powers india
also i would say it's one of the major
powers whether you like it or not it is
in some ways
so these are the countries
that would be involved in a major war
a small country like nepal would would
be a bystander a small country like
bangladesh
or or new zealand
or paraguay
or whatever you know or or ghana or
whatever these countries will be
bystanders they'll be just
watching them from the sidelines they
will not be involved in a big war
it is the major power that will be
involved in a big war and it is these
countries that will
that will uh take the major brunt the
major impact of this
of whatever
cyber warfare is unleashed
on each other
so the the impact on underdeveloped and
developing countries won't be very
significant those countries will just be
bystanders they'll be watching and
seeing what's happening that's all
so
yeah that's what i can say
okay hypothetically in your view if
india were to go against the indus water
treaty and force pakistan to consider
and make drastic policy and leadership
changes
force them to shift alliances it's
prudent to break bend your opponent when
they're down
diplomacy and dialogue is wasted as they
are cornered this very moment what
geopolitical repercussions should be
prepared to face if any
so the thing is this
no country
needs to adhere to any treaty that is
unfair
and the indus water treaty is one of the
most lopsided treaties in human history
i think about eighty percent of the
waters
of the uh drainage system in the suburbs
in the region is allocated to pakistan
and that's what india willingly signed
away
our great great magnificent
magnanimous
statesman of the prime minister sri
jawal nero he decided that we should
give away 80 plus of the waters of this
region to pakistan we will only take 20
because we are so magnanimous
right we want india to grow at two
percent one percent per year so that's
the kind of individual mr the great
shari neroji was the panditji
and that's what
we are currently uh in this this is the
treaty that still holds it was brokered
by the world bank or imf or something
i'm not sure look it up look it up
please i may be
marginally off in that but uh the thing
is this
no nation
can be forced
to comply with a treaty that is unfair
to it look at the chinese
they had this treaty with the uk
the hong kong treaty
uh one nation two systems they broke the
treaty
this was supposed to be a treaty that
was supposed to last a certain number of
years or maybe in perpetuity i'm not
sure look it up but they broke it
recently they said that we don't we no
longer believe in this treaty this
treaty will no longer
be honored by us
and what could the british do nothing
they could just sit and protest feebly
so if you are a strong power a strong
military power a strong diplomatic and
economic power then you can do whatever
you want you can break treaties
india
i would say should not
um keep on
you know complying with the indus
productivity but to
go against the treaty
you need to first build up the
infrastructure
to divert the waters and use them in a
proper way
so for that you need dams you need a
system of dams in the region
that can divert the waters and store
them on indian soil and deny the use of
all that water to pakistan has india
done that in the past 70 years
nothing
even in the past seven eight years we
have not built a single dam in this
region so all we can do is talk that we
will
we will
all we can do is threaten you know empty
words that you know we may not in the
future
adhere to this treaty but it's empty
words unless and until you have the
capability to divert the waters at any
given point in time
then your threats are no longer empty
then your threats threats can be
turned into actions
so i would say that india needs to first
build a number of dams
on these rivers
which would enable india to divert the
waters
then we can actually go ahead and do
what is best for us from our national
interest perspective which is stop
giving pakistan 80 of the water for free
right
i mean the chinese control so many of
the rivers today
uh the rivers that go into into india
into pakistan into nepal and bangladesh
into southeast asia
and they don't have any such treaty with
anybody which means that they can do
whatever they want and the rest of the
world has to just
well
uh grin and bear it
so why can't india also do the same to
pakistan so for that we need to first
build the infrastructure the dams on the
rivers and then we can do whatever we
want
and if we are powerful enough
then there will be no geopolitical
repercussions if you are a weak country
small economy three trillion dollars
and then we do such big moves
then you may face problems from other
countries
especially from china
who may try to arm twist india in a
variety of ways because
pakistan is a chinese client state
so india needs to become a much more
powerful country first and in the same
time india needs to build up the
infrastructure of dams
in this region
so once india is a powerful economy
let's say 10 trillion dollar economy
with a military capability that is
proportional to that then india will be
able to do these things without facing
any geopolitical repercussions
so it's a long-term game we need to
build up our economy and military in the
meanwhile and build up
the dam infrastructure
okay ghost coder says most of the
scientists believe that consciousness
has nothing to do with quantum physics
as a physicist yourself what are your
views in the double slit experiment and
the observer effect okay so first of all
i don't agree that most scientists or
physicists believe that consciousness
has nothing to do with quantum physics
uh so let me let's let's uh
elaborate a little bit about that
so what is the double slate experiment
what is the observer effect so the
double slit experiment is essentially
when you have a target
and you have a gun that shoots particles
at the target let's say you're shooting
electrons at a target at a screen
you're shooting electrons at the screen
and between your electron gun and the
screen you put
a double slit
so it's it's it's a it's a
it's a screen
with two slits in it
so when you shoot
you the electrons at your at your
big target in the way there is the
screen with two small slits so most of
the electrons will hit the screen and
bounce back and some of the electrons if
you aim them properly will go through
one of the two slits and what you find
is that
when you shoot electrons like this at
the target through these two slits
on the
target you find an interference pattern
the kind of pattern you would find if
the electron was not a particle but a
wave so if you have water waves going
through two slits then after they emerge
from the slits they interfere with each
other and form an interference pattern
the same sort of thing you see on the
screen
the target right when you shoot
electrons at the double slit
and you find this even if you shoot one
single electron at a time
which tells you that these electrons are
interfering with themselves
the electron is interfering with itself
so that is the weird thing about quantum
physics now if you place a detector just
before the slit which is called a which
way detector to see which way the
electron is going
then it stops behaving like a wave it
starts behaving like a particle and you
no longer find the interference pattern
on the screen
so this is called the observable effect
the moment you make an observation
of the electron before it goes through
the slits it's the act of making the
observation
transforms the electron from
[Music]
a wave into a particle so in quantum
physics what you have is that particles
are essentially
probability distributions
they don't have any any clear property
or even position
until you make an observation of the
particle that's when it resolves and
focuses into one in one place and that's
where it becomes physically significant
until you make an observation the
particle doesn't even exist in one place
it may exist in multiple multiple places
at once so that is the thing about
quantum physics so there are a number of
interpretations of quantum physics there
is the copenhagen interpretation which
says that a measurement causes the
collapse of the wave function
and there is no consciousness involved
in that then there is the von neumann
wigner interpretation which says that
consciousness is integral it is it is
fundamental
to the uh
to the collapse of the wave function so
it is a consciousness it is the presence
of a conscious observer that causes the
collapse of the wave function and then
you have the uh you have hugh everett
interpretation the many worlds
interpretation which says that your
observation which you're making is only
in this universe but the other
probabilities are for other universes
parallel universes so every time you
make an observation the universe
branches off into two branches and
and that's what happens so so so that's
the many worlds interpretation so there
are a number of interpretations of
quantum physics one of which
the quantum uh
font neumann
wigner interpretation says that
consciousness is central
to the collapse of the wave function and
there are experiments in which you make
a measurement but you don't see it for
instance you can record a quantum state
as one of the uh
energy levels of an atom
so no
human observer
actually observes this it is simply
recorded in the energy levels of an atom
and yet this causes the collapse of the
wave function
so then how does that work now if no
consciousness is accessing it so one of
the philosophical
uh
arguments is that the universe itself
has a consciousness a greater
consciousness and even if a human
conscious observer doesn't see it the
universal consciousness records the
observation and and makes takes note of
it and that's why the wave function
collapses so these are all philosophical
arguments to a great extent what this
tells us is that we don't understand
quantum mechanics
properly
there may be hidden variables
in the theory or we may even have super
determinism
which means that everything is
determined from the very beginning from
the very
instant of the big bang itself
so we still don't know quantum mechanics
is a big mystery
so what i would say is that we don't
know i
you know because we still don't have
enough information and the quantum
mechanics especially the foundations of
quantum mechanics are
a field
of very active research and nobody has
any answers today there are strong
beliefs among there are these different
camps that physicists are now divided
into some believe that the copenhagen
interpretation the shut up and calculate
interpretation is the correct
interpretation that has been the
mainstream view for a very long time
today the many world's interpretation
has a lot of
uh supporters many people many
physicists believe in that
the von neumann wigner interpretation
also has its its supporters and
proponents so you know what it's all a
matter of personal belief right now
what really appeals to you what you
really believe deep inside
but from a physics perspective we still
don't know so that's what i can say as
of today
we still don't know for sure what
quantum mechanics is telling us and what
lies
deeper at a deeper level in quantum
mechanics we still don't understand that
okay ritesh says is it possible that the
three-dimensional space that we
experience
itself expanded out of the point mass at
the time of the big bang and there was
nothing a space before the before in the
larger universe
the entire universe see the best theory
that we have of the origin of the
universe is the so-called big bang
theory right
so according to this theory everything
that we observe was inside that
point mass that the universe was so at
the very beginning
the entire universe that we can observe
and whatever it lies beyond that also
was all compressed into a single point
so called singularity
all of space all of time all of matter
all of energy was compressed into that
small into that one singularity that
little point
so everything that we have today it all
came out of the point the entire
universe was compressed into a small
single point
right so there was no larger universe
beyond that that was all that was the
there was all there was in the in the in
the universe according to the best
theory that we have
so it is not possible the theory says
that everything came out of that
all of space all of time all of matter
all of energy everything
dark matter dark energy whatever we call
it
it all came out of that one single
point which is the big bang singularity
according to loop quantum gravity it may
not have been a singularity it may have
been a quantum
the smallest quantum of space time but
well these are different theories we
still don't know which way which
uh
which of these ideas is correct but the
best theory is the big bang theory and
that's what we know from it
what would have been the difference if
the french ruled instead of the british
well see it's like this the british were
able to rule india
because they controlled okay let's go to
the map
so this is the map of the world
you know where india is
it's here if you can see my mouse
pointer
and this is england the united kingdom
over here
now this small island this country here
was able to control india
occupy india for a couple of centuries
and plunder everything of value out of
it right
so they were able to rule india for a
couple of hundred years first through
the east india company and then through
the uh
british crown itself now see the
distance between the uk and india
it's about seven eight it's about seven
thousand kilometers that's how far this
place is so how were they able to rule
india from so far away it's because they
were able to control the entire
region between
their country and india
they were
essentially ruling over the entire
region
they had
the infrastructure in place they had the
supply chains in place
they had diplomatic
relations in place which facilitated
facilitated everything they were doing
they had the system of supplies regular
supplies ships
and land routes and all that in place
so that is the reason why the british
were able to rule india for so long and
the french also wanted to
uh
take over india napoleon was very
ambitious he first conquered egypt he
tried to conquer egypt with the purpose
with the overall long-term objective of
eventually
displacing the british from india and
occupying and colonizing india so even
napoleon wanted to do that but he was
not able to place the infrastructure
he was not able to create the
infrastructure and put it in place that
would have allowed him
to rule india from so far away so that's
where he failed but in case the french
had been able to do it
then not just india but the entire world
would be speaking french today
instead of english
so that is the difference we would have
been speaking french today and the
french were just as brutal as the
english okay they also perpetrated all
kinds of atrocities in india
they also destroyed temples and built
churches over them
it's well known
so the french would have been just as
brutal just as barbaric as the british
they were all animated by the same
culture and the same objectives of
plundering and looting
a peaceful country
so there would not have been much
difference
for
at the end of the day for the ordinary
indian citizen
the only difference is that we would be
speaking french today
so that's the only difference
and not just india but half the world
mostly would have been speaking french
okay ishvara moody says indians had
influential trade with east africa in
the medieval period but why is it that
today we have negligible trade influence
in east africa what are the barriers to
this
so it is well known that india has had a
presence in east africa for centuries
maybe thousands of years
we know that there is a presence of
indian cattle the indian indus valley
zebu cattle
in africa for thousands of years
it is known that these cattle were
present in egypt about four thousand
years before today and there was an even
older wave of integration introgression
of indian cattle into africa which
happened about 10 000 years ago so india
has had and these cattle they don't go
on for a walk on their own
they don't migrate on their own they
only migrate with humans so this tells
you that indians have had a presence in
africa for about 10 000 years at least
in eastern africa right
and if you look at the culture of east
africa if you look at the uh
if you look at see this is east africa
here
starting from somalia ethiopia kenya
tanzania malawi mozambique madagascar
all the way
to southern africa so this entire east
of course of africa if you go there and
if you look at the culture there you
will see very very strong
influences of indian culture there in
the cuisine if you look at the cuisine
of eastern africa it is very similar to
indian cuisine in a variety of ways
the kind of spices they use the turmeric
the all the indian spices they use the
way of cooking the way of the
preparation it's very indian you can see
india right in there if you look at the
dressing uh the kind of clothing the
wear
you can see influences from india
from western india from gujarat
especially in eastern africa
and even the genetics may be deeply
influenced by india so you see all of
this
in east africa which shows that india
has had very ancient links with east
africa for a very long time at least a
thousand years most likely about 10 10
000 years so what happened
why do we have nothing no influence
there today well because india was
enslaved for the past thousand years
it's very simple the answer is very
simple why did india lose its influence
in east africa why did india lose its
influence in southeast asia in the past
thousand years because india was
enslaved
the past 1000 years of our history have
been the millennium of humiliation the
millennium of enslavement we were first
enslaved and occupied by the turks
and then by the europeans the british
they destroyed india's economy they
destroyed india's culture civilization
they destroyed india's architecture
temples everything
and reduced india to a rootless rootless
deracinated country that it is today a
people
a nation of people with low standards of
relation nation of people with very low
confidence
right
and if you are a nation with low
standards low confidence
no understanding of your past your
history then you will have no influence
anywhere and nobody will respect you
so that's what happened and that's why
we have negligible influence there today
and what happened in africa also is that
africa itself was enslaved by the
arabs first of all
so you had the
the islamic slave trade that happened in
africa which is not documented at all it
was a terrible terrible period
and lots and lots of africans were
enslaved and taken off
and carted off like animals to the
arabic countries to central asia etc
some of them survived most of them died
you don't see any
african origin people there today which
shows what happened to those to these
unfortunate slaves
so uh
because of this slave trade much of the
culture of africa especially eastern
africa was totally destroyed annihilated
and then you had the european
colonization which
destroyed whatever was left of africa it
impoverished africa
it destroyed
everything that was left of african
culture of african civilization
and everything of value was sucked out
of africa all mineral resources all
wealth all gold everything was sucked
out of africa by the europeans
and every problem that exists in africa
today
is a consequence of the european
destruction of africa
right
and that totally eradicated whatever was
left of india's influence in east africa
and other parts of africa so that's what
happened all of this is a consequence
of the past 1 000 years
of depredations
in india in africa by by these uh
by these colonial powers
okay uh the next question is you said
that shingis khan the great mongol
conqueror refused to invade india
but as we see his empire he conquered
the whole of afghanistan and more more
than half of pakistan
and also some parts of burma and
arunachal your views
also in allowed in kilojoules brutal
rain
mongols invaded india six times okay see
the video i made
is about why chung is khan refused to
invade india it has nothing to do with
what happened afterwards so let's not
talk about what happened afterwards what
the later mongols did
let's talk about shingis khan and his
policy so like you say
he did conquer the whole of afghanistan
you are absolutely right
he conquered afghanistan which is here
he conquered significant portions of
present-day pakistan which is right
and this happened in the 13th century
so at that time afghanistan was india's
gandhar province and pakistan was just
western india
today these are separate countries but
in the past it was all part of india
so you are right that he conquered
significant parts of india now when you
talk about arunachal pradesh in burma no
that is not correct he did not ever
venture into arunachal pradesh or burma
chinese khan did not ever go into those
regions but he did conquer the entirety
of afghanistan and significant parts of
what is now called pakistan
so
then how can i claim that he refused to
conquer india
so let's understand something
let us understand something
the parts of india
that he conquered
in his pursuit of the coward jalaluddin
kharagmi
those parts of india
were culturally no longer indian
afghanistan was already
way way way transformed its culture was
eradicated
and by the time afghanistan was already
fully islamized and turkish-sized
and the parts of pakistan present-day
pakistan that ching is conquered again
had already
to a large extent been totally
culturally and religiously transformed
right
so the parts of india that he
conquered
with the parts of india that had already
been
transformed culturally into something
that was not indian at all
right
but he stopped at the indus river sindhu
river and he refused to go further even
though jalaluddin
escaped and crossed the river alone
leaving his
women fork behind
chinese khan said it doesn't matter he
is done he's destroyed i have destroyed
his army i've destroyed him as a person
he's no longer going to matter and i
don't want to go further into india
because i have no enmity with the people
of india and i've given the reasons why
he refused to conquer india you can look
at the
the video
but the parts of india that chinese khan
did conquer were actually no longer
culturally or civilizationally indian
so that
in a way tells you that there was a
cultural and civilizational reason also
why he refused to go further because he
did not want to spill the blood of
people
who practiced indian culture and
religion because he
clearly had some sort of respect for
that
and he did not have the
the same respect for the other culture
which is nearly wiped out
so
that's what i can say that's oh these
are just facts
okay saurabh says why don't why didn't
linguists
linguists linguistic researchers
work hard together and try to decipher
the indus valley script as it may be a
foundation to other scripts like brahmi
as some people point out the resemblance
between some of these signs of the
scripts you know what
it's because they have never had any
interest
in
resolving this issue
because if you try to if you succeed in
deciphering the indus script
it's going to point towards sanskrit i
know lots of people are going to say no
no no it is tamil it is dravidian
nonsense there is zero evidence for that
zero evidence whatsoever
but there are clear similarities between
the indus valley saraswati valley script
this the symbols of the script and
brahmi letters
there are clear similarities between
brahmi
and indus valley
symbols script symbols right
and this has been remarked upon by
various researchers
including uh let's say
dr subash
you can look up his articles he has
remarked upon that and he is actually
in a way deciphered
a passage
or or a number of a sequence of of
symbols
in the indus valley script
and
turns out to be sanskrit
so if
if these linguists go ahead and do what
they are paid to do
and they discover that this is sanskrit
then it is going to destroy whatever
arguments these linguists have been
making
of the iron invasion right
see the aryan invasion theory is the
foundation
it is the bedrock upon which all the
breaking india forces
uh
do their propaganda
they want to say that india is a nation
that has been conquered by
ancient white skinned aryans
and all the people of north india and
western india are the descendants of
these evil invaders and hinduism is
foreign to india sanskrit is foreign to
india these are invasive
this is an invasive language invasive
culture invasive religion india needs to
be freed of hinduism and sanskrit and
all that
essentially this is just a way of
abrahamising in india
so the aryan invasion narrative the iron
invasion myth
or migration myth tourism myth
whatever you want to call it it is the
foundation of all these claims
and if the indus valley script the
saraswati valley script is deciphered it
will put this lie to
it will kill the lie once and for all so
they don't want this to happen
and today india's academia
is controlled by india's enemies
the problem in india today
is that we have handed over our
education system to the enemies of
indian culture and civilization
we have handed over
the media
to the enemies of indian culture and
civilization we have handed over the
entertainment industry to the enemies of
india's
culture and civilization but the worst
thing is the academic system the
education system
so everything a child learns
is anti-india and
hinduism anti-everything anti-indian
culture
so if this script is deciphered it will
be a terrible
fatal blow
to
all the claims that people make
right
and that's why they are unwilling to do
this so what needs to happen is that we
need to
do this linguistic research from scratch
a priori by first of all discarding all
the assumptions that linguists have made
in the past
we need a bunch of young linguists in
their 20s ideally with a proper
grounding in the scientific method
and
they need to start with
start
analyzing all of this from scratch
and if you want to
have a foundation in the principles of
linguistics you can start with the
grammar of panini
and we can also
have a good grounding in tamil grammar
for instance just for comparative uh
purposes
and
this entire process needs to be done
from scratch from a scientific
perspective factual data driven
perspective not based on all kinds of
colonial assumptions
so if you do that if you bring a bunch
of bright young minds together 20 30
people
you give them sufficient funding you
give them a good salary and you give
them five ten years they're going to
crack it
they're gonna crack it very easily
and you can see clear similarities
between this ancient script
and
the brahmi script for instance so it's
it's a matter of time you know it's just
that these people are unwilling to do it
so that's the
big problem in india today
sunny says according to you which is the
best form for any ruler to rule
what is the best form of governance is
what he is saying centralized or
decentralized because in ancient india
we have seen the mauryans mauryan empire
which was centralized and the gupta
empire which was decentralized and both
of them were excellent
i am puzzled about the centralization
and decentralization please explain it
the guptas were never decentralized
no empire
that rules over an enormous land mass
like india can ever be decentralized
if you are too decentralized you no
longer rule
right
so if you look at the form of governance
either in the mauryan era or the gupta
era during skanda gupta or um
etc it was a strongly centralized system
of governance of course there was
delegation of authority to regional
governors
for instance uh let's take the example
of the great uh some other gupta the
great conqueror the gupta who who
reunified india under indian rule
so he went on a lifelong military
campaign he conquered every single
kingdom etc that was in india and
unified everything under his empire and
his policy was very simple for instance
he had a powerful navy he went all the
way down south and conquered most of
southern india as well he defeated all
the local kings and then he reinstated
them
so he reinstated these kings as his
vassals
the agreement the arrangement was very
simple you guys are being reinstated as
kings you will continue to rule as you
have always ruled but
the condition is very simple you are
ruling on my behalf
i am your overlord i am
the supreme maharaja dhiraj of india i
am the emperor of india you are ruling
on my behalf and every year you will
collect taxes and send me some taxes
so that was the thing
so that was in a way hands off ruling
but it was still very centralized
because all of these kings they would
have
representatives
of the ambassador overseeing them and
everything was transparent to them to
the emperor
and these kings who would be ruling
independently supposedly
would still be answerable 24 by 7 by 365
to the emperor and they could not
implement any policy
without the express approval and consent
of the emperor so it was delegation of
power but it was still a very strong
centralized rule
so in india today they talk about
federalism india has a very good federal
structure there is a lot of delegation
of power to the states you know what
india is a very weak country today there
are states where india the where the
central government's reit doesn't even
properly
run anymore
look at
certain states well i'm not naming
anybody
but there are certain states where the
prime minister
is not even safe in if he goes there
he's not even safe physically
right
and there are there are other states
where the borders are open and all kinds
of foreign foreigners are allowed to
come in and change the demographics
so this federal structure this
decentralized structure is weakening
india from within
india has become a very soft state very
weak state because because of the
structure and this structure was put in
place by the british during the transfer
of power in 1947 to keep india weak they
never wanted india to become powerful
again
and we are continuing
what they have given us
how how incredible is it
how many years has it been since our
so-called independence seventh decades
we are still slavishly following
the order the british gave us
so
i am very clear about this a country as
large as india
needs very strong central rule
decentralization is the death
of a large
of an enormous
country like india it will not last long
if it stays decentralized the way it is
today
okay
what do you think about china deploying
war robots and remote control vehicles
which carry machine guns and in the lac
the line of actual control so india and
china have an enormous
the undemarcated border thousands of
kilometers long
and one here's news reports that the
chinese have deployed certain robotic
machines
remote controlled vehicles with machines
etc at the lse
well
it is inevitable that the future of
warfare is going to go in this direction
you're going to have
autonomous systems
autonomous killing systems in war in the
future you're going to have robots
you're going to have drones that
operate autonomously without human
inputs these drones will loiter in the
air and they will decide whom to kill
based on algorithms
without any human inputs at all
so that is the future of warfare like i
have said many times it doesn't matter
anymore how brave your army is when you
are fighting robots who have no fear
your bravery is pointless it's useless
and many people disagree with me well
feel free to disagree but this
this is my perspective
the future is going to be about
technology
you may have the bravest soldiers in the
world but if your technological
level is less advanced than that of your
adversary you are doomed
so what do i think about what the
chinese are doing first of all i don't
know how good their technology is
everything they do is called psyops
psychological operations they're just
trying to psych you out
so first of all uh the chinese
technology still isn't that good what i
would say is that we should develop our
own robotics our old our own autonomous
killing machines
right develop
these robotic machines and deploy swarms
of these robots on the on the lse in the
air underwater
everywhere
we have to embrace high technology we
have to embrace
21st century cutting-edge technology
otherwise we'll be left behind
so the chinese understand this i
i believe india is also
nowadays in the past few years
focusing on high technology
we have certain uh uav et cetera
programs u uv programs also underwater
uh autonomous vehicles
so these things are being developed in
india as well and we need to deploy them
and we need to make sure that they are
better than those of our adversaries
that's what india needs to do
anish says
modern science is majorly dependent on
observations to record data
and to come up with theories and
explanations
doesn't it do injustice
to reality that is phenomena taking
place which aren't observable to humans
will never be considered
knowing half the truth is more dangerous
than not knowing the truth how can
modern science tackle this shortcoming
of itself
so you know um
let's let's go back to a different time
period let's go back 5000 years before
today
uh when we have this
phase of our civilization called the
sarasvati hindu phase of civilization
so this was a highly urbanized
phase of our civilization you had
multi-state buildings you had these
well-planned cities excellent drainage
systems high technology uh seafaring
culture we had
very high technology ports and harbors
and all that
how did we develop this
we developed this with science and
technology and the science that we had
at that time four thousand five thousand
years before today
was the modern science of that time
correct
now do you think that in the modern
science of that time our ancestors
included things that could not be
observed
invisible or or unobservable phenomena
no
we in india have the have had the
world's longest and oldest scientific
tradition
pure science i'm talking about i am not
talking about philosophy or spirituality
i'm talking about pure science we have
had
the world's oldest longest and most
advanced scientific and mathematical
tradition
and this was pure science in indian pure
science also
we did not
uh include unobservable
phenomena
and unphysical objects
right our scientists also
were pure scientists they did not mix
philosophy or spirituality with science
otherwise india would not have been so
advanced
to be an advanced civilization you have
to
focus on material progress
apart from other kinds of progress
cultural spiritual philosophical all
that happens but first of all to be the
most advanced civilization you have to
focus on material progress
and material progress can only happen
through pure science what is the
definition of science science is the
study
of
physical objects and physical observable
phenomena nothing else
that is the hard boundary of science
and that's what our ancestors used
to
make india the world's most advanced
civilization
so i have nothing against
uh
people doing research in
unobservable unphysical phenomena
talking about things like the soul
atma
spirit all that but these are not
observable these are not quantifiable
these are not measurable objects these
are not physical objects
so these cannot be placed into the
domain of science it's very simple that
is the hard
boundary of science science only deals
with physical objects and observable
phenomena
right
everything else falls under the realm of
philosophy or spirituality it is a
different discipline
i am not saying it is a bad discipline
it is a discipline you should laugh at
no not at all these are very serious
disciplines they all have their place in
society and in the progress and
advancement
of humanity
but this is that that is not science
that's how it is
so this is not a shortcoming of modern
science this is a discipline that
science
has to follow so that it doesn't go off
track
that's just the way it is
okay dia says
do you think humans can get super powers
by meditation or is it a myth do you
believe that himalayan yogis have
miraculous powers
um
so
there have been questions in the past i
have taken these questions about uh the
question has been like is it possible
for humanity for human being to utilize
a hundred percent of the brain
right
and what i said is that we are already
using a hundred percent of the brain but
we are not using it effectively
so
when you meditate
it's all about
stilling
your mind
but quieting your mind down and
see the thing about the mind the human
mind is that it's very noisy
try and sit quietly for 30 seconds and
see where your thoughts go a million
directions
all kinds of thoughts are constantly
going on in your mind
so you are constantly utilizing 100
of your mind but it's just noise noise
noise noise
random noise
uncontrolled noise you have no control
of what's happening in there
just observe your your mind for 30
seconds if you can be quiet in and all
alone and that's what you will see so
meditation
is about quieting that noise down it's
about stilling the mind
and
focusing
and focusing on itself so there are
various techniques of meditation you
focus on your breathing pranayama is
part of that ve passionate also also has
this technique of of uh just observing
your breath and
trying to remove everything else there
is transcendental meditation meditation
and all other kinds of different
meditations they all originate in india
and the common thing is that you are
removing all the extraneous noise and
you just
shutting all of that down
what you what you achieve by doing that
is that then when you focus your mind on
something
it is truly focused on that there is no
noise
and that's where you get what seems to
be like super powers
so for instance yogis in the himalayas
we can see videos of that
there is a lot of evidence for this
they have the power of being completely
immune to sub-zero temperatures
these yogis will wear very little
clothing just loin cloth or something
saffron
they'll be topless
their legs and arms will be bare and
they will be sitting in the snow for
hours and days and weeks and they will
not freeze to death
right you see that again and again and
again
this
if you were to do it if i were to do it
we would freeze in 30 seconds we would
freeze to death in 30 seconds to five
minutes
instantaneous death in the himalayan
temperatures minus 20 minus 30 degrees
these guys it doesn't affect them
and there have been studies medical
studies scientific studies about
done on these yogi's
monks etc
they they are placed in these mri
machines and then they go into a
meditative trance
and they measure the brain waves and all
that and they can see that the brain
wave patterns are very very different
almost like some kind of superpower and
they can even achieve certain physical
effects that are
essentially unheard of
so these effects
are all achieved by
stilling your mind and focusing it
properly on whatever you're trying to
achieve and if you can really focus the
entirety of your mind on that then you
can achieve things that look like
superpowers right so it's not unphysical
it's not supernatural it's just the
power of the human mind
and nowadays this is being repackaged in
the west in various forms
there is this
individual called vim hof who has stolen
uh these ancient indian
traditions
the tradition of pranayama and the
tradition of exposure to cold weather he
calls it the vim hof method
i would call it the wim hof method of
cultural theft nothing else
so yeah so it is suddenly possible to
attain what looks like superpowers by
meditation it is not a myth but it's
also not superpowers it is all
within the realm of possibility if you
know if you can discipline yourself to
to achieve those mental states
okay dv says if we make sanskrit of our
national language is it best that we
have a gradual approach
for a span of a few years or straight up
make it our language and how do we teach
people who don't go to school at a mass
rate
see any big change cannot happen
overnight
if you want to make sanskrit india's
national language it has to be at least
a 20-year plan a very well planned
phased rollout of sanskrit as a national
language it has to happen through the
education system and through the
government
machinery
right
so what you would typically do is you
would start
by first educating the teachers in
sanskrit every teacher should have a
certain level of proficiency in sanskrit
and then you start with the lowest level
in education from from kindergarten
junior kg single kg then first year
second year third year and then you do
it year by year so the the generation
that started with sanskrit at the lowest
level in the kindergarten
they will be the first generation that
will do the entire schooling in sanskrit
and the next generation also the next
year also can continue with that so it
has to be a slow phased rollout
nationwide it may take a generation it
may take 20 years maybe 30 years
but
you can take the example of israel how
they were able to do it
they themselves had
lost their cultural language hebrew it
was it had gone out of use for at least
thousand years but they were able to
revive it and today it is their national
language it is their vernacular language
it's the language in which they conduct
their day-to-day life so it can very
much be done sanskrit has been out of
use for about 150 years only
before that it was the
medium of education throughout india
this is well attested so it can
certainly be done but it cannot be done
overnight it has to be done in a phased
manner over a period of 20 or 30 years
that's the way you would do it properly
and bring it back into the mainstream
okay let's take one more question for
today sachin says can you provide some
background on me
and his so-called atrocities against
buddhist stupas and monks
many marxist historians paint this as
hindu destruction of both the dharma in
india thank you
so much a hunnic king
he was in power in
northwestern india
present-day punjab present-day pakistan
presented afghanistan
he had a sizable kingdom
and he was in power in this region i
think somewhere in the fifth or sixth
century most likely the sixth century so
he was a horn he was a hunnic invader
now the horns typically
apart from maher cole
assimilated into indian population into
and they they absorbed indian culture
they became indian by culture and
practice
but mihir kul was an exception
so there is a chinese traveler whose
name i forget it was not fahean or
shwanzang it was somebody else
he had come to india at the time and
what he records is that this individual
miracle was a complete barbarian
he was not a believer in any god he was
a godless person he was an atheist
and all his subjects were unhappy under
his rule
so he persecuted
the brahmanas
he persecuted the teachers of the vedas
he persecuted the the buddhist monks he
destroyed buddhist stupas
and
he was hated all around nobody was happy
under him neither the so-called buddhist
neither the so-called hindus no neither
the so-called brahmanas nobody was happy
under his rule he was just a barbarian
and barbarian not by blood but by action
okay so that's the kind of guy miracle
was
later uh
hunnic rulers were very much indian
they even defended defended india from
the turks
against the turks in the future but
mihir kul was an exception a godless
barbarian who persecuted all
all these people whether they're
brahmanas or buddhist practitioners or
monks or anybody else everybody was
unhappy under his rule now you're right
the marxist historians try to portray
miracle
as a shaivite
i think
if you if you
look at i think the encyclopedia
britannica or something
in there mihirko is is portrayed as a
practitioner of shaivite hinduism
without any evidence whatsoever but if
you look at the account of the chinese
traveler who came to india and who took
back lots of
dharmic texts back to china eventually
if you look at his account
it is clear that mehirekul did not
practice any religion whatsoever he was
not a dharmic person he was an ur
dharmic person he persecuted
all dharmic people so these
this portrayal of miracle is a hindu is
a lie it's an outright
fabrication
all right
excuse me assuming
okay let us take a couple of questions
from the comments from the from the live
chat
do you guys have some questions
that i should take from the live chat if
you have any
let me know ask some questions and i
will take a few
before we end this
uh
this particular session
uh one second
so lily joshua says tamils are the
descendants of whom the tamils are the
descendants of the ancient indians from
10 000 years ago
see india is the original founder zone
of the out of africa migration the out
of africa migration happened about 75 80
000 years before today
and this bunch of humans homo sapiens
who came out of africa crossed over into
asia let me show you where
they crossed over into asia
around here
uh sorry not there around here
there is this
strait called the baba al-mandab strait
it is over here most likely that the
migration the crossing over from africa
into asia happened
and these ancient humans they traveled
across the coastline and eventually
the first place where they made a
permanent settlement was india the
indian subcontinent this happened about
70 000 years ago and india is the
world's uh
is the oldest out of africa founders
zone
and today's indians are the descendants
of those ancient migrants so our
ancestors have been in india for about
70 000 years
we are the oldest non-african population
in the entire world
so the tamils and all other indians are
the descendants of those ancient indians
that's all i can say and this is proven
genetically i i have a podcast with dr
niraj coming up in two three days
please watch that podcast and see what
he has to say about this
okay saurabh says why are we not
excavating dwarka gujarat we we need to
ask the asi we need to ask the
government of india why are we not
excavating dwarka why
it is a travesty
we have this place which is known to be
the place where lord krishna ruled in
the days of the mahabharata
we have this sankan city
exactly where the mahabharat says
this sunken city would be found we have
found it but we are not excavating it
what is the reason
because these people they don't want the
people of india to know the truth about
their history
so that's why they are not excavating
they will spend all their
budget location on restoring turkic
monuments mughal monuments but they will
not invest it in excavating
dwarka and preserving
and doing proper research on either the
bait dwark island the island of dwarka
or the sunken city so let's see where is
dwarka beit dwarka see this is dwarka
this is the modern town of dwarka and
off the coast of this modern town of
dwarka
just off the coast we have the sunken
swedish city somewhere around here i'm i
don't know exactly where it is but it is
somewhere around here and then you have
the island of beit dwarka
and you can see how it is being
encroached
you can see how this island
is being encroached
you can see the encroachments all over
this is
a historical treasure of of india's
civilization and see what's being what's
being done there
wait another 20 30 years and the board
will take over this island
so that's where we are
so it's just unfortunate
why don't you
why don't you sing it sir the ussr
national anthem i i am not
adept in singing that particular song
it essentially used to say that we are
indestructible
right
which is something that
turned out to be false
my views on shark tank india well i
haven't watched any episodes so i can't
say but i think it's a good idea it's a
it's a better kind of reality show than
what is it that they have a
big brother or whatever i think shark
tank
would be a much better way much better
reality show people can actually learn
something from there
um
okay what else do we have
he was not a barbarian he was woke he
practiced equality outstanding
yep
yep yep
i am sure mihir kul was woke he was not
a barbarian
uh today's marxists and today's
historians would call me
woke egalitarian person i'm sure maybe a
feminist as well
uh
what else do we have
okay i think i'm gonna end it here
it's been an hour and 45 minutes so
thank you everybody for your questions
very interesting questions as always and
i'm i once again apologize to those of
you whose questions i have not been able
to take
i can only take 20 30 questions per
session i get hundreds
per week thousands per week so i am
sorry to those of you whose questions i
could not take
but i tried to take questions that would
be
uh
that would impart some good knowledge to
all of you so that's that's the emphasis
that i have and that's what we'll keep
on doing so i will see you tomorrow
tomorrow is a live chat session so i
will see you there be ready with your
best questions and let's have an
interesting session tomorrow same time
same channel until then thank you very
much
and i will see you tomorrow thank you
bye